טוב, Tov,
today's דף daf is פג, Pe Gimmel, 83, פג, Pe Gimmel, that's
דף daf we're on today. And we pick up with from the
middle of פג, Pe Gimmel, where it is מיתיבי, Meisive, about 2,
3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10 lines down, line starts with
אין קרבן לחציין. Ein Korban Lachatziyin. So to remind you the context,
the גמרא Gemara had a fascinating debate between רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan
and רב אסי, Rav Assi, I'm sorry, and רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, which is a woman takes a נדר neder
for two things, one is עינוי נפש inuy nefesh and the other
isn't, "I won't eat these two loaves", one of them not eat
would be עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, the other would not be. And
the, what do you call it, and according to רב יהודה אמר
שמואל, Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, he can be, you know
when he's מיפר meifer for one, it works for both. Is that
because of an idea of like נדר שהופר מקצתו הופר כולו, neder
shehufar miktsato hufar kulo, which is sort of what I would have
said. Or is it an idea that the way the ר"ן Ran
frames it in a slightly different way, not that the result of
being מיפר meifer part causes the rest to fall away, but that
you have to be מיפר meifer the whole thing, and in order
you'd be מיפר meifer the part that you're entitled to be מיפר,
meifer, you the husband, the תורה Torah therefore entitled, you know, enabled
you to be מיפר meifer all of it, that's sort of the
way the ר"ן Ran frames it. And רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says
no, the part you're מיפר meifer you're מיפר, meifer, the part you're
not you're not. Also worth noting that when it comes to the
issue about דברים שבינו לבינה, devarim shebeino leveinah, we said explicitly that
the husband is מיפר meifer his part and the rest remains. So
that might be a different type of category, but this is דברים
devarim of things of עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. So then the גמרא
Gemara challenged רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan with an idea that when the
husband is מיפר meifer נזירות, nezirus, the whole thing falls away, even
though the only part that's really עינוי נפש inuy nefesh is the
wine part. And the גמרא Gemara basically said נזירות nezirus is all
one package, even רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan would agree that you cannot
have the end result of partial נזירות. nezirus. So there it is
true, when you remove part of it it all falls away, נזירות
nezirus is different. And that's then, that was the phrase of אין
נזירות לחציין, ein nezirus b'chatzayin, there's no half status of a נזיר.
nazir. Which then led אביי Abaye to clarify or to push back
and to say it's not just אין נזירות לחציין, ein nezirus lachatziyin,
there's no קרבן נזירות לחציין. korban nezirus lachatziyin. What does that mean?
It means the same way you can't be a נזיר nazir just
for some things and not for other, it also means that when,
and this is relevant specifically to the husband being מיפר meifer the
נזירות, nezirus, though when the husband ends the נזירות, nezirus, though the
woman has now only observed half of it. Right, it's not like
she never was a נזיר. nazir. She was a נזיר nazir for
the first 15 days. So for example, right, and here's a question,
if she, and basically this is the assumption, let's say she violated
her נזירות nezirus on day 3, and then the husband was מיפר
meifer it on day 10, right, she would still get let's say
lashes if she willfully violated with התראה hazraah the נזירות, nezirus, even
though it doesn't apply from day 10 on, it was still fully
in force until day 10. Okay, so but nevertheless, even though it
was full, a full נזירות nezirus until it was until the הפרה,
hafarah, there's not going to be a קרבן נזירות korban nezirus because
if you don't complete the 30 days, you never get to the
state of bringing a קרבן. korban. Okay, so that's what we're saying,
you cannot be a partial נזיר, nazir, if the husband annuls part
or whatever, even if you were to try to annul part, even
if there's only עינוי נפש inuy nefesh for part, it all gets
annulled, and when it gets annulled, then there's not going to be
any קרבנות korbanot because the period was not completed. And now we're
going to question, turn our focus to this issue of קרבן נזירות
לחציין, korban nezirus lachatziyin, of whether that's actually true or not. Yes?
I just want to clarify, it's not necessarily 30 days, let's say
she did נזירות nezirus for 60 days.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, right.
45, she still wouldn't bring a קרבן. korban.
Right, so that's actually an interesting question. If she, somebody who's מקבל
mekabel on themselves a נזירות nezirus for, I was wondering that question,
you know, yes, you can be a סתם נזירות שלשים יום, stam
nezirus shloshim yom, but you can be מקבל mekabel a נזירות nezirus
for longer.
And if a normal person is מקבל mekabel a נזירות nezirus for
60 days, he or she can't say on day 45 I'm just
going to bring a קרבן. korban. You can't because your נזירות nezirus
isn't over. But it is an interesting question, and I don't know
the answer, let's say a woman was מקבל mekabel נזירות nezirus for
60 days and the husband was מיפר meifer it after day 30,
right. So there it really is over and she really did 30
days, she just didn't do the full amount that she was נודר.
noder. So there I actually don't know. Yeah, I don't know, I
had thought I was wondering the same thing, so I don't know
the answer to that. All right, so let's take a look now
at the גמרא. Gemara. So גמרא Gemara says מיתיבי, Meisive, I'll ask
you on this idea that there's not a halfway that there's not
a קרבן נזירות korban nezirus for doing it only part way. האישה
שנדרה בנזיר, Haishah shenaderah bineziur, a woman made a נדר neder to
be a נזיר. nazir. והפרישה בהמתה, Vihifrisha behemtah, and she separated out
her בהמה. behemah. Now the ראשונים Rishonim say that the context here
is
that she became טמאה. tameia. It's not so spelled out explicitly in
this ברייתא, braisa, but that's the context, she became טמאה. tameia. Now
when a woman becomes טמאה tameia she brings two קרבנות. korbanot. She
brings an עולת העוף, olas haof, חטאת העוף, chatas haof, and and
a animal that is, I forget which animal it is, anyway that
is an אשם. asham. That's anyone, right, not just a woman, thank
you, that is true. Okay. So she basically brings those three things.
Okay. So what she did is she separated out the larger animal
for the אשם, asham, and then ואחר כך, ve'achar kach, and she
didn't yet separate out or... ring or whatever her עולת העוף olas
haof or חטאת העוף, chatas haof, she became טמאה. tmeia. And the
interesting thing about being טמאה tmeia is that you bring a קרבן
korban even before your נזירות nezirus is done, right? You bring a
קרבן korban in the middle of your נזירות nezirus to restart it.
Okay, ואחר כך הפר לה בעלה. veachar kach hefer lah baalah. And
then the husband was מיפר. meifer. So nevertheless, even though she's not
a נזיר nazir anymore now, she was טמא tamei and she was
obligated in קרבנות, korbanot, but she's no longer a נזירה. nezira. So
does she continue to bring the קרבנות? korbanot? What does she do?
So it says מביאה חטאת העוף ואינה מביאה עולת העוף. mevia chatas
haof ve'eina mevia olas haof. She brings the חטאת העוף chatas haof
part of the קרבן korban but not the עולת העוף. olas haof.
Now the obvious before we even get to why only the חטאת
העוף chatas haof and not the עולת העוף, olas haof, the just
the textual question here is what about the אשם? asham? It says
she was הפרישה בהמתה. hifrisha behematta. So does she bring the אשם?
asham? Does she not bring it? And why did you say that
she was מפריש mafrish it without telling us what you do with
it? So nobody really knows what the story is. If you take
a look at תוספות, Tosfos, תוספות Tosfos says here, תוספות Tosfos says
like this,
it's in the wide lines here of תוספות Tosfos four, five, six,
seven, no, but eight lines down of the wide lines which starts
with the word תימה. teima. So תוספות Tosfos says like this,
וקשה בין מאן דנקט נקט והפרישה בהמתה. vekashe bein man denakat nakat
vehifrisha behematta. What purpose did the ברייתא braisa mention that she separated
out the בהמה behema and then it didn't do anything with that
statement? ולמה לא פירש אחר שהפרישה מה יעשה בה? velamah lo peireish
achar shehifrisha mah ya'aseh bah? And why didn't it tell us what
the status of that בהמה behema was? What's the story of the
אשם? asham? So he just leaves it as a question. So bizarre.
Mentioned separating out the אשם asham and then doesn't tell you what
you do with it, doesn't tell you if she's going to bring
it. So I don't know more than תוספות Tosfos on that. I
don't have the secret answer. But anyway, we're now going to focus
on the fact- who knows what the story is with the אשם,
asham, but we're going to focus on the fact that the only
thing she brings is a חטאת העוף. chatas haof. Okay.
But wouldn't it have made a difference if she was מפריש mafrish
let's say the עוף of and not the אשם? asham?
It doesn't sound like it, but that's what's so bizarre about this
ברייתא. braisa. Why discuss הפריש? hifrish? Why discuss the אשם? asham? I
don't know. All right, so anyway let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. Okay, ואי אמרת אין קרבן לחצי נזירות, ve'i amart ein korban
lachatzi nezirus, if you can't have a קרבן korban for a non-completed
נזירות, nezirus, אמאי מביאה חטאת העוף? amai mevia chatas haof? Why is
she bringing a חטאת? chatas? The fact she's bringing a חטאת העוף
chatas haof proves
that there is some status to her נזירות nezirus even when it's
cut off. Now I have to tell you before we even get
to the answer, first of all the obvious question is then why
isn't she bringing all the קרבנות? korbanot? But besides which, bringing the
קרבנות korbanot for being טמאה tmeia is less interesting because you bring
קרבנות korbanot when you become טמאה tmeia even before the נזירות nezirus
is over, right? So that might be a very different story. Might
be you never bring the קרבנות korbanot for the completion of the
נזירות nezirus if you didn't complete it. But you could say that
even though she's no longer- even though a standard person who brings
קרבנות korbanot for being טמא tamei brings it while they're still a
נזיר, nazir, because the whole purpose of bringing קרבנות korbanot when you're
טמא tamei is to restart the נזירות, nezirus, you could still imagine
that even if they're no longer a נזיר nazir because the husband
was מיפר, meifer, there's still some קרבנות korbanot that still need to
be brought. She was still obligated, she became טמאה, tmeia, she was
still obligated, right? Maybe there are some קרבנות korbanot that need to
be brought. So to say you bring קרבנות korbanot for being טמאה
tmeia and some of them is not as- is not- does not
seem so relevant to the question of would you bring קרבנות korbanot
for the completion for a נזירות nezirus that had never completed. So
anyway that's the גמרא's Gemara question. You see that you're bringing a
קרבן, korban, at least a חטאת העוף. chatas haof. Doesn't this show
you bring a קרבן korban for a partial נזירות? nezirus? So the
גמרא Gemara says, ואלא מאי? ve'ela mai? So what do you want
to say? יש קרבן לחצי נזירות? yeish korban lachatzi nezirus? You want
to assume oh look, you see you bring קרבנות korbanot for an
uncompleted נזירות nezirus and that's why you bring a חטאת העוף? chatas
haof? If that's true, שבקה לתנא בפלוגתא דאייתי? shavkah letana beplugta de'aytei?
Then why do we only find out this case of טומאה tumah
where she brings one קרבן? korban? Why didn't it tell us a
more a bigger point? That a normal woman who's a נזירה nezira
and her נזירות nezirus ends brings your standard three animals, חטאת עולה
ושלמים. chatas olah ushlamim. Okay, this is not the חטאת- chatas this
is not for חטאת עולה ושלמים chatas olah ushlamim is for a
normal נזירות nezirus that completes. So it's saying look, the idea that
she brings a חטאת העוף chatas haof and that's in another a
similar type of thing to the point we were saying. The idea
that she brings a חטאת העוף chatas haof when she became טמאה
tmeia is not indicative that for a partial נזירות- nezirus for a
for a נזירות nezirus that was ended halfway in that you would
bring the קרבנות. korbanot. Because if that were true, why not just
say that? Say a woman who was a נזירה nezira and the
husband was מיפר, meifer, she brings her קרבנות, korbanot, she brings all
three קרבנות. korbanot. So clearly that's not true. Clearly this is some
special case because of טומאה tumah and it's also a special case
that she's only bringing one of the קרבנות, korbanot, the חטאת העוף,
chatas haof, and she's not bringing the others. So this is not
at all indicative that in general you would bring the קרבנות korbanot
if you had not yet completed the נזירות, nezirus, right, if the
husband cut it off. There's something very specific here about it bring-
about being a state of the קרבנות korbanot of טומאה tumah and
about the fact that it's only a חטאת העוף. chatas haof. So
what's the explanation? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא לעולם אין קרבן
לחצי נזירות. ela le'olam ein korban lachatzi nezirus. You do not bring
קרבנות korbanot for an incompleted נזירות, nezirus, the standard קרבן. korban. Now
what is
the... Now what does that mean and what's the doubt here?
So it means specifically a חטאת העוף chatas ha'of and what it's
really doing is it's saying a חטאת העוף chatas ha'of ironically, because
as Michael correctly says, normally if there's any type of a קרבן
korban that you need to be definitely obligated in, it's a חטאת,
chatas, right? A חטאת chatas you can only make something a חטאת
chatas for a concrete חטא. cheit. If you don't have a concrete
חטא, cheit, it's not a חטאת, chatas, it's an אשם, asham, all
these types of things.
However, the גמרא Gemara in another place says, not about a נזירה,
nezira, but about a general story about a woman who had a
miscarriage and she doesn't know if actually that miscarriage made her טמאת
לידה tumas leida or not. Was it after forty days of conception,
not after forty days of conception? What exactly was the story? Now
this woman could be caught in perpetual limbo because a woman who
gives birth, even or even who has a miscarriage after forty days
of conception, is טמאת לידה. tumas leida. She cannot eat קרבן, korban,
she cannot go up to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash until she
brings her special קרבן לידה, korban leida, okay, יולדת, yoledes, and that
קרבן יולדת korban yoledes is a חטאת העוף. chatas ha'of. Okay, now
the only problem is is that what can she do? If she
can't bring, she in theory should be stuck. Because since she might
not be טמאה, tmeia, so then she couldn't bring the חטאת העוף.
chatas ha'of. If she is טמאה, tmeia, then she needs it to
become טהורה. tehora. What is she going to do, right? So how
could we let her bring the חטאת? chatas? Maybe she's not טמאה,
tmeia, then a חטאת chatas you can't have a חטאת chatas if
you're not חייב chayav in a חטאת. chatas. So the גמרא Gemara
learns out from פסוקים, psukim, basically it has a מסורה masorah that
this woman could bring a חטאת העוף על הספק. chatas ha'of al
hasafek. You bring the קרבן, korban, you sprinkle the blood, the animal
isn't eaten, and that makes her טהורה. tehora. That actually there is
this phenomenon of a חטאת העוף chatas ha'of that is בא על
הספק. ba al hasafek. At least we know that, the only one,
this at least we know by יולדת. yoledes. So what the גמרא
Gemara is now saying is, given that we've now introduced this idea
of something like of a קרבן korban that is not really being
brought, you know, in a definite way, but it's brought because somehow
it's necessary to serve some type of a function, you know, that
otherwise that needs to get served, we're going to assume that somehow
we can use that same idea of a חטאת העוף chatas ha'of
to solve another type of a vague ambiguous gray type of a
situation. So here's this woman who became טמאה בנזיר, tmeia b'nazir, so
she actually did become טמאה, tmeia, she became חייבת chayaves in a
קרבן, korban, so in one way she's obligated in a קרבן. korban.
In the other hand, though, she's no longer a נזירה, nezira, and
there's no נזירות nezirus to restart because her husband was הפר. meifer.
So does she bring a קרבן, korban, does she not bring a
קרבן? korban? I mean she, you know, she should bring a קרבן
korban for the past, but she can't bring a קרבן korban to
restart it. What's her story? So very conveniently, one of the קרבנות
korbanos that's brought
for a נזיר nazir who becomes טמא tamei is a חטאת העוף.
chatas ha'of. So by analogy essentially what we're going to say is:
ah, we know about a חטאת העוף chatas ha'of by a יולדת.
yoledes. A חטאת העוף chatas ha'of is a type of a thing
that you can bring when you're stuck and in this sort of
indeterminate state. I mean if the תורה Torah already is obligating a
חטאת העוף, chatas ha'of, you would go ahead and bring it anyway,
right? So this woman as well. Now she's not exactly stuck because
she doesn't need it to become טהורה, tehora, but she's in this
gray zone, not so much a ספק safek zone but as a
more like a בין השמשות bein hashmashos zone, a zone that's inherently,
you know, in a gray area, נישט אהין נישט אהער, nisht ahin
nisht aher, right? And therefore how that, so in that situation, the
חטאת העוף chatas ha'of still works perfectly for that situation. It works
to address the fact that she became טמאה tmeia even though she's
no longer a נזירה. nezira. Okay, that seems to be a very
interesting sort of way the גמרא Gemara is understanding why we picked
on חטאת העוף. chatas ha'of. The ראשונים Rishonim also point out, you
know, in the גמרא Gemara another גמרא Gemara that deals with this
same ברייתא braisa says it also helps for the fact of the
idea of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, if you remember, that says a
נזיר nazir is a חוטא, chotei, right? שציער עצמו מן היין. shetzi'er
atzmo min hayayin. And therefore there's an idea that that needs atonement
as well. So because she became טמאה tmeia and she has this
idea of חטאת chatas not as a טהרה tahara process, right, which
is what the חטאת chatas here is functioning as part of making
her טהורה, tehora, not really about חטא, cheit, if you know like
by the woman, the יולדת yoledes also the חטאת chatas is more
about becoming טהורה tehora than about חטא. cheit. Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara
says there's also a value of bringing this חטאת chatas also even
though she became even though she's no longer a נזירה nezira because
of like atoning like a נזיר nazir who becomes טמא, tamei, the
atonement for שציער עצמו מן היין, shetzi'er atzmo min hayayin, for that
depriving that they did in the very essence of being a נזיר.
nazir. All right, so that's basically the גמרא's Gemara answer. We see
this woman brings a קרבן, korban, the חטאת העוף. chatas ha'of.
Doesn't that show that a woman whose נזירות nezirus is cut off
still brings קרבנות? korbanos? And the answer is: no, give me a
break. If that were true, you would just tell me a regular
woman whose נזירות nezirus is cut off brings all the קרבנות. korbanos.
So clearly, you do not bring the standard קרבנות korbanos when your
נזירות nezirus gets cut off. And she's only bringing one of the
קרבנות. korbanos. She was טמאה... tmeia... Ah, so clearly it’s not the
general rule that you’re still obligated in the קרבנות, korbanot, it’s but
given this reality that she did become טמאה, teme'ah, she did violate,
even though she’s no longer a נזירה, nezira, right, that reality says
that at least one of the קרבנות korbanot makes sense to still
bring and particularly conveniently we have this קרבן korban called חטאת העוף
Chatas Ha-Of which we know gets brought to these ambiguous types of
situations, so she presumably would not bring the אשם, asham, not bring
the עולה, olah, she would just bring the חטאת העוף, Chatas Ha-Of,
yes.
If she hadn’t become טמאה, teme'ah, she wouldn't have brought any. Correct.
So then why should we say that there’s any connection to the
נזירות nezirus about this חטאת? chatat?
You mean about this denying yourself wine? That aspect?
What I’m saying is that the חטאת chatat is because she was
טמאה, teme'ah, right? Okay, so why should we associate it with this
question about is she bringing a partial קרבן korban because of the
נזירות? nezirus?
That’s the גמרא's Gemara’s answer, that’s exactly the גמרא's Gemara’s answer, that
it does not prove that point, exactly,
exactly, the גמרא Gemara saying
right, meaning meaning meaning if
a normal woman would not bring קרבנות korbanot for a נזירות nezirus
that ended in the middle, right, and this is clearly only a
very special case, it’s only a case when she became טמאה teme'ah
and only one of the קרבנות. korbanot. So the fact that it’s
given such specific and narrow circumstances shows that the general rule is
that a woman does not bring קרבנות korbanot for ending a נזירות,
nezirus, for it being terminated in the middle, yeah.
I'm not sure I understood this correctly, I mean because the impression
I was getting is that you bring a קרבן korban for טהרה
tahara purposes but I thought it was more for קרבנות korbanot purposes,
right? I mean it's once she goes to the מקווה mikveh she
can go to the בית המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash, right?
No, no, no, no, when any somebody anybody needs a מחוסר כיפורים
mechusar kippurim and needs a קרבן korban to become טהור, tahor, then
before they're טהור tahor they cannot eat קרבנות korbanot and not enter
into the בית המקדש. Beis Ha-Mikdash.
I mean let's say she actually wants to bring her קרבן, korban,
what is she going to do?
She stays outside the מקדש Mikdash grounds and somebody else brings it
for her.
But she's still עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim though, right? Yeah, okay, she
just can't go any further.
Correct. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, all right,
so basically דווקא davka it’s the opposite, from the fact that we
gave only special circumstances of טומאה tumah and only one of the
קרבנות korbanot shows that the rule is that if your נזירות nezirus
is cut off because you’re a woman and your נזירות nezirus is
cut off by your husband you do not bring the standard קרבנות.
korbanot. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, מיתיבי, meisivei,
I’ll ask you,
איתיבי, aitivei, I’ll ask you, and now we’re dropping the קרבנות korbanot
discussion which is like okay that’s good because that’s a נזיר nazir
discussion which is getting a little confusing, we’ll get to נזירות nezirus
soon enough, okay? I mean we’re still going to be discussing נזיר
nazir but we’re getting back to the bigger question of can you,
the husband, be מפיר mefir half of the נדר, neder, right? If
part of it was עינוי נפש inuy nefesh and part of it
was not, that debate of רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan and שמואל, Shmuel,
can the husband be מפיר mefir half or when he does half
the whole thing goes off? Let’s take a look. מיתיבי: meisivei: האישה
שנדרה בנזיר, ha-ishah she-nadrah be-nazir, and the other woman becoming a נזיר,
nazir, ונטמאת, ve-nitmeis, and she became טמאה, teme'ah, ואחר כך היפר לה
בעלה, ve-achar kach heifer lah baalah, and then the husband was מפיר.
meifer. All right, sounds familiar. מביאה חטאת העוף ואינה מביאה עולת העוף.
meviah chatas ha-of ve-einah meviah olas ha-of. Okay, so we just, it
sounds pretty familiar, we just said that, but now let’s see what
the גמרא's Gemara's going to do with it. ואי אמרת מיפר למתענה
ואין מיפר לשאינו מתענה, ve-i amart meifer le-misaneh ve-ein meifer le-she-eino misaneh,
if he's מפיר meifer for the part that is about self-denial and
not the part that's not about self-denial, דילמא מיין דאית ליה צערא
היפר
לה, dilma mi-yayin de-is leh tzaara heifer lah, מטומאת מת דלית ליה
צערא
לא היפר לה, mi-tumas meis de-leis leh tzaara lo heifer lah, maybe
how do you know that just because he was מפיר meifer that
she stopped, right, the essence is the reason she only brings one
of the קרבנות korbanot and not all of them is because basically
her status has completely ended, right? This case of the woman who
became טמאה. teme'ah. So says the גמרא, Gemara, how do you know
her status has completely ended? Let's say the הפרה hafarah only worked
for the wine and it didn't work for the טומאת מתים tumas
meisim because טומאת מתים tumas meisim is not to be able to
נטמא למת nitma le-meis is not exactly an עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh.
Oh my god, I can't go to a cemetery, that's not, well
depends who's all right, all right, we'll see what the גמרא Gemara
responds, but first we're assuming it's not an עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh.
Okay, big deal, let's assume that were true. So therefore the גמרא
Gemara says well, if therefore he annulled the wine part but she's
still not allowed to become טמאה, teme'ah, then since the part of
the נזירות nezirus of not becoming טמא tamei still is part of
her, she's still a נזיר nazir for טומאה tumah purposes, then it
would seem that she should be able or she should be obligated
to bring all the קרבנות korbanot because the קרבן korban is for
the sake that she became, is because she became טמאה, teme'ah, and
if that's the part of the נזירות nezirus that still sticks with
her and she has to now complete her נזירות, nezirus, maybe she
can drink wine but she can complete her נזירות nezirus in the
status of being not becoming טמא למתים, tamei le-meisim, then she should
have to bring the normal קרבן korban to resume the נזירות nezirus
and complete the נזירות nezirus in the at least regarding the טומאת
מת, tumas meis, okay? That's the How can you be a נזיר
nazir and So
thank
you very much, so the question of course is what type of
question is this? We just said yesterday that it's a package deal,
you can't remove the wine part and leave on... the grapes part.
So as like and you can't remove the wine part and leave
on the טומאה Tuma part. That's crazy. So the ר"ן Ran says
an interesting הוה אמינא Hava Amina that the גמרא Gemara had, which
is he says look, we're gonna find out in נזירות Nezirus that
there is a נזיר Nazir called נזיר שמשון, Nazir Shimshon, which actually
is, what do we know about שמשון? Shimshon? He didn't cut his
hair until whatever the last scene there. He didn't drink wine, but
he was becoming טמא למתים tamei l'meisim every other day, right, in
terms of killing the Philistines. So the גמרא Gemara learns from there
that even though נזירות Nezirus is a package deal, there is something
called נזיר שמשון, Nazir Shimshon, which is just about מתים meisim and...
which is just about wine and hair and not about מתים. meisim.
Now even there, let's say somebody did not call it נזירות שמשון.
Nezirus Shimshon. Somebody just said, הריני נזיר Hareini Nazir for
ייין yayin and for and for and for hair. Would that person
be a נזיר? Nazir? Or would we say no, it's all a
package deal. If you want to be a נזיר שמשון, Nazir Shimshon,
you have to ask to be a נזיר שמשון. Nazir Shimshon. But
you can't be standard נזיר Nazir just for A and B. Standard
נזיר Nazir it's all a package deal. That's anyway point number one.
But what the ר"ן Ran says is he goes even further. He
says, well, if you could have נזיר שמשון, Nazir Shimshon, which is
just the wine and the hair and not the מתים, meisim, then
in theory, you could also have the reverse. Cause you see you
could separate out the מתים meisim from the other two. So then
in theory, maybe you could be a נזיר Nazir just for מתים
meisim and not for wine and hair. מעכב הקרבנות Me'akev ha-korbanos then?
Well, that's what least the גמרא's Gemara's הוה אמינא Hava Amina that
if as long as the קרבן korban was for the טומאה, Tuma,
and you're still in that type of a נזירות, Nezirus, maybe we
should go normally. Anyway, that's still a crazy idea, right? We've never
heard of that possibility before at all. The only exception we have
is נזיר שמשון. Nazir Shimshon. Even that, when you have to label
it as נזיר שמשון, Nazir Shimshon, that you should be able to
just have it for just מתים meisim seems crazy. So nevertheless the
ר"ן Ran says the גמרא's Gemara's toying with that הוה אמינא. Hava
Amina. Or maybe, says the ר"ן, Ran, the גמרא Gemara obviously knows
that the answer is like it said before, that נזירות Nezirus is
a package deal. So obviously you can't just be the נזיר Nazir
for the מתים. meisim. Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara just wants to raise
the issue for the sake of the answer. So let's see what
the answer is.
אמרי יוסי, Amri Yosei, טומאת מת Tumas Meis נמי nami is ליה
leh צערא. tza'ara. No, טומאת מת Tumas Meis also, not to become
טמא למתים tamei l'meisim also is something of an עינוי נפש. inui
nefesh. Why is that? דכתיב De-ksiv והחי יתן אל לבו, v'hachai yitein
el libo, the living will place to the heart when, you know,
in terms of when somebody dies and going
to
a בית אבל. beis avel. דתניא De-tanya ותנא ברייתא, v'shanah braisa, היה
רבי מאיר אומר, haya rabbi Meir omer, מאי דכתיב mai de-ksiv והחי
יתן אל לבו? v'hachai yitein el libo? דיספד De-yisped יספדון ליה. yispedun
lei. If somebody eulogizes other people, then when he dies he'll be
eulogized. דיבכון De-yivkun יבכון ליה. yivkun lei. דיקבר De-yikber יקברון ליה. yikberun
lei. If somebody goes and bury somebody, he'll be buried. If you
come to my funeral, I'll come to yours, okay, promise.
Anyway, so,
alright. Anyway, so, so what the גמרא's Gemara's saying is, to say
like Michael said also if it's a relative or whatever, I want
to visit the grave and general, as part of being a social
part of the community and doing my duties and responsibilities or whatever,
to not be able to do that, to go to a funeral,
to go to a בית קברות, beis kvoros, could be an עינוי
נפש. inui nefesh. So therefore the גמרא's... Gemara the ר"ן Ran says,
look, obviously the גמרא Gemara could have said that obviously you can't,
you know, get rid of the נזירות Nezirus for one and leave
the other. It's a package deal. But by making this point that
saying that even going to a... becoming טמא למתים tamei l'meisim is
עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, right, that there's a נפקא מינה. nafka mina.
So if a woman takes a נדר neder and says, forget נזירות,
Nezirus, a woman just takes a נדר neder and says, a נדר
neder that she's not going to go to become טמאה tmeiah or
go to a בית קברות beis kvoros or go to a funeral,
the husband could actually annul it. That's considered a נדר neder of
עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, denying herself, right, it's very, I think, poignant
and powerful, denying yourself that thing is really that sense of real
afflicting yourself in terms of your membership in the community and how
other people perceive you and so on, and are you doing your
responsibilities. So in the end, the bottom line is we remain with
the debate of שמואל Shmuel and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. If half
of the נדר neder is עינוי נפש inui nefesh and the other
is not, can... does he wind up annulling the whole thing or
only half of it? That's debate number one. But everybody agrees by
נזירות, Nezirus, it's all a package deal. And since you can be
annulled the wine part, then it all goes away. Yes, Michael.
So then my question then is then, if broadening the category of
עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, then would that extension apply to say a
woman says, alright, I'm not gonna go visit my friend?
Yeah, I mean, right, I think it raises a really good question.
Right, and you know, and of course remember the irony that the
גמרא Gemara wanted to know whether according to the רבנן Rabbanan denying
sex is עינוי נפש inui nefesh and it didn't... and it left
that without resolving it. And here we say not going to a
בית קברות beis kvoros is עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. So, you know,
it definitely seems that we're more and more broadening the category, but
you know, it is funny the things that the גמרא Gemara did
not at least explicitly resolve earlier.
But you can see
that it probably would be.
Yeah, alright, I mean, yeah, alright.
You said such a point about going to a funeral is just
like the ultimate חסד chessed because they can't do anything for you,
and here we're talking about another side about.
Oh, you know, that's a nice point. You know, that's a nice
point, you're right, you're right, because normally we talk about taking care
of the dead as a חסד של אמת chessed shel emes because
you don't expect anything back from that person, but here the גמרא
Gemara is sort of reflecting on a reality that that person isn't
going to give you any gratitude back but as a sense of
the community and yeah, it's a very it's a good point, very
good point. Okay, so let's take a look at the next משנה.
Mishna. קונם
שאני נהנית לבריות. Konam she-ani nehenis l'vriyos. Now, of course, you have
to remember that it's the grammar's always confusing, the ל lamed also
means מ, mi, so what so when says קונם נהנית ל Konam
nehenis l' means from really. So the woman is saying forbidden to
me any benefit I would get from creatures, from people. So she's
forbidding to herself all
benefit that
she would receive from people. Okay, אינו יכול להפר, eino yachol l'hafer,
he cannot be מפר. meifer. Now that
sounds crazy. What do you mean? If there's anything called עינוי נפש
inui nefesh more than forbidding herself from benefit from all people, it's
got to be that. So what the גמרא Gemara is going to
say is that the the גמרא Gemara is going to understand this,
that when a woman says something like this 'from all people', she
implicitly means not her husband, okay, meaning all other people. And therefore,
since her husband can still go ahead and provide for her whatever
things she might need, even if she can't get benefit from everybody
else in the world, right, she can still get benefit from her
husband. And therefore, it's not עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. Now even saying
that is a little bit bizarre, right?
Because they're going to go, we're broadening the category of עינוי נפש
inui nefesh and we've seen that this would fit into it too.
Well, okay, this is generally saying it's broad, but here the specific
point is, is that is it enough that she can get it
from one source and not from other sources? Because didn't before we
say, right, that if somebody basically says 'I'm not going to get
benefit from like, you know, from the פירות peiros of this person',
that the husband can be מפר meifer it, because at least it's
עינוי נפש inui nefesh in terms of from that person, right? So
here isn't this exact even broader, it's like I can't get benefit
from everybody. The fact that she can still get it from her
husband, right, so how does that really like you know how does
that really play out? So the גמרא Gemara so although actually hold
on a second here. Yeah, so the ר״ן Ran asks that, and
let me remind myself what the ר״ן's Ran answer is, he says
like this, he says like this one minute.
Yeah, so basically what he says is the following thing. He says
because he's also talking about how it relates to the whole story
about the חנוני, chanvani, the storekeeper, right? And if you remember that
case about the storekeeper, if your primary stuff comes from one storekeeper,
right, then that is considered עינוי נפש inui nefesh because then you're
totally sealing off that one avenue. Okay, so the ר״ן Ran says,
but I don't get it, like, okay, this storekeeper is sealed off,
but the husband can still provide for her, and here she's sealing
off everybody in the world. What difference does it make if the
husband can still provide for her? Isn't it a problem that she's
sealing off for herself everybody in the world? So if you take
a look at the ר״ן, Ran, here's the answer, he says לא
קשיא הוא, lav kushya hu,
it is one, two, three, four, five, wait, one, two, three, four,
five, six lines down, wait, six? Five lines down in the widest
lines, middle of the line. The line starts with the word כחנוני.
k'chanvani. Okay, he says, לא קשיא הוא דהתם אסרה עלה פירות חנוני,
lav kushya hu d'hasam assra
aleha peiros chanvani,
when she says I won't get the fruit of that storekeeper, אפילו
בזמן שיביאם לבעל. afilu b'zman she'yaviam l'baal.
So it doesn't matter, even if the husband goes to the store
and buys the fruit, it's still the fruit of that storekeeper. So
if the only place where we can buy our groceries, nobody else
will sell us groceries, okay, we've been bad on our credit, bad
on
our debit, nobody will sell us groceries except this one store, and
if I say the groceries from that store are forbidden, then there's
no way we're going to get it. My husband will go, but
but even if he goes and buys it and brings it, I'm
still getting the groceries of that store, even though I'm getting it
through my husband. So that completely seals it off when I say
the grocery, those are the only stores that will sell me groceries
and I've totally made them off limits. כדי אמרן לעיל. k'dei amran
l'eil. הלכך יפר, hilkach yafar, therefore he can annul it. אבל הכא
לא אסרה הנאת פירות הבריות. aval hacha lo assra hana'as peiros ha'briyos.
I didn't say I won't get the gro- groceries or the food
from all other people. What I said was הנאת הבריות, hana'at habriyot,
I won't benefit from people, which means a direct benefit. הלכך כל
היכא שבא לוקח אותם מותרת בהן. Hilkach kol heicha she'ba lokeach otam
muteret bahen. So here's how my life is still tolerable. You, David,
and Jonathan, and right, and everybody here, and Joe, you're not- I'm
not going to directly get anything from you. I'm going to send
my husband Michael, okay? And if I need to borrow your rake
or your car or get an apple or a pound of sugar,
Michael's going to go there, get it from you, and then give
it to me. And then who am I benefiting from? I am
then seen as benefiting from my husband, I'm not benefiting from you.
So if I said all of your objects, the objects of the
whole world are forbidden to me, then that is עינוי נפש. inui
nefesh. That's all off limits, right? Just because I got Michael to
give me the whatever he has, all your stuff is off limits.
That's עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. But as I said I won't get
הנאה hana'ah from you, that's about the direct interaction. And the fact
that Michael can sort of serve as the shell company here and
the intermediary and I'd be- and I'll be seen as benefiting from
him, therefore it's not considered enough עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, because I
still have access through Michael to all your stuff, and therefore it's
not עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. Right?
Because then I could say like, this is really annoying.
I have to go out and get everything. Yeah, but that doesn't
seem like בינו לבינה. beino l'beinah. It seems like it has to
be directly about the dynamics. As we saw before, things that are
annoying, like just because
you won't be nice to my brother or to
my son or whatever, right? That wasn't enough of בינו לבינה. beino
l'beinah. Why isn't her husband considered in the category of all people?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss. But yes,
literally it is, but implicitly it's not. Implicitly we assume when she
says I won't get it from anybody, she means you know other
than the husband. That's how we read it. Okay, so it is
very challenging. Here it is, she says I'm not going to get
benefit from anyone. Oh, that's not עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, because she
can still get from the husband. So the רן Ran to tone
it down a little bit says, the husband can indirectly- she can
get indirectly from everybody else through the husband, and therefore it's not
enough עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. The other thing I want to say
to you, right, and Michael's saying, what do you mean? We keep
on expanding עינוי נפש inui nefesh here so narrow, is remember the
גמרא Gemara. before said that all of the פרק perek is the
position of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi has a
very narrow definition of עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. So since it's רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, therefore who's very narrow, he's not going to call
this עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. Okay. So that's point number one. אינה
יכולה להפר. Eina yachola l'hafer. Now, ויכולה היא, v'yachola hi, in addition,
she can benefit בלקט שכחה ופאה. b'leket shikchah u'pe'ah. She can actually
go ahead and collect the gleanings. That's not considered benefiting from people,
because since people actually make it הפקר, hefker, so when she picks
it up, I'm not getting benefit from Boaz's yard if I'm Ruth
here, right? I'm getting benefit from the stuff that's already הפקר. hefker.
Okay, so- so I'm not actually benefiting from the person. The person
had a מצוה mitzvah to leave it behind, to make it הפקר,
hefker, and I'm just getting from nobody. I'm getting from God. Okay.
Now if somebody says קונם כהנים ולויים נהנים לי, Konam Kohanim u'Levi'im
nehenim li, a קונם, Konam, כהנים ולויים Kohanim u'Levi'im cannot get benefit
from me. Okay, so this is no longer about הפרה, hafarah, because
you're not denying yourself to get benefit, you're saying כהנים ולויים Kohanim
u'Levi'im cannot get benefit from me. There's only a little bit of
a problem, which is that you have to give תרומה ומעשר, trumah
u'ma'aser, and therefore how can you make that forbidden to them? You're
obligated to give that to them. So יטלו על כרחו. yitlu al
karcho. Then they can take against your will, because that was not
something that you had the power to make forbidden. That was something
that they fundamentally had a right to, was the תרומה ומעשר. trumah
u'ma'aser. If, however, you say כהנים אלו ולויים אלו נהנים לי, Kohanim
eilu u'Levi'im eilu nehenim li, that these particular כהנים ולויים Kohanim u'Levi'im
will not get benefit from me, then fine, then יטלו אחרים, yitlu
acherim, then give your תרומה ומעשר trumah u'ma'aser to other כהנים. Kohanim.
Okay, so this has nothing to do with husband and wife. This
just has to you know do with the fact that are there
other people that are being still you know whatever we're dealing with.
Since we dealt with מתנת עניים, matnat aniyim, we're going to deal
with מתנת כהונה. matnat kehunah. Okay, let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara, אלמא, Alma, says the גמרא, Gemara אפשר דמתזנא מדיליה.
efshar d'mitazna midilei. If the husband can't annul it, then obviously she's
not totally forbidden on the whole world, she can still be- get
benefit from the husband, be support- you know, be sustained by the
husband. So the גמרא Gemara says מכלל דבעל לאו בכלל בריות הוא.
michlal d'ba'al lav bichlal briyot hu. The husband is not included in
the phrase בריות, briyot, right? So you know, so husbands are not
human beings. Alright, anyway. But anyway, when she says all people, she
doesn't mean- she means everybody else when she says all people, right?
You know, so- okay. So therefore, and that's presumably why the נדר
neder is not עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, because presumably the husband isn't
included. So the גמרא Gemara says אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look
at the end of the משנה. mishna. ויכולה ליהנות בלקט שכחה ופאה.
v'yachola l'ehanot b'leket shikchah u'pe'ah. She can benefit from לקט שכחה ופאה.
leket shikchah u'pe'ah. אבל מדבעל לא אכלה. Aval mid'ba'al lo achla. But
presumably not from the husband. Now, where do you get that from?
Just because she can get לקט שכחה ופאה, leket shikchah u'pe'ah, how
does it mean not from the husband? So the רן Ran says
the גמרא's Gemara question is, if she's still being sustained by the
husband, she's not- she's not poor. Right? When it says she can
get לקט שכחה ופאה, leket shikchah u'pe'ah, it- it suggests the idea
that she has nowhere to get from except לקט שכחה ופאה. leket
shikchah u'pe'ah. And the רן Ran says but that's not true. If
she can still get from the husband, right, then ולקט v'leket then
she's not poor. poor, and just in terms of the laws of
לקט שכחה פאה, Leket Shichachah Peah, not the laws of נדרים, Nedarim,
she shouldn't be entitled to collect yet from לקט שכחה פאה. Leket
Shichachah Peah. So what's פשט? peshat? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
ומי בבעל לא אכלה, amar u'mi b'ba'al lo achla, אלמא בעל בכלל
בריות הוא, alma ba'al b'chlal briyot hu, the husband is included. So
the גמרא's Gemara going to have three answers. אמר עולא, Amar Ula,
לעולם בעל לאו בכלל בריות הוא, Le'olam ba'al lav b'chlal briyot hu,
it's like you thought. The husband when she says 'all people', she
doesn't mean the husband. She can still benefit from the husband. ועוד
אין יכול להפר מפני שיכולה ליהנות בלקט שכחה ופאה. Ve'od ein yachol
lehafer mipnei she'yechola lehenot b'Leket Shichachah u'Peah. And what the ברייתא Baraita
is saying: look, number one, the husband can't הפר hafer because he's
not included in, because she can still get from the husband, so
she's not totally forbidden in getting benefit in, in, you know, it's
not total עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. And number two is, even if
the husband had no food and was poor and so on, she
would also still be entitled to get לקט שכחה פאה. Leket Shichachah
Peah. So it's another way in which she's not totally sealed off
from the world, because she can get לקט שכחה פאה. Leket Shichachah
Peah. But the real point is, is that if she was poor
and if the husband were poor, but the real point is that
it's not עינוי נפש inui nefesh because the husband can still provide
for her. Okay, by the way, the ר"ן Ran says that what
partly is what's bothering the גמרא Gemara is, is that if the
woman genuinely said, 'I won't get benefit from anybody in the world
including my husband', the fact that she can still be survive on
הפקר hefker is still not enough, it still would be עינוי נפש.
inui nefesh. The ability to survive on לקט שכחה פאה Leket Shichachah
Peah does not make it not עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. And the
proof of this is when the גמרא Gemara. says, when she says
'I won't get from this storekeeper' and he's the only storekeeper that
provides, even רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi admits, if you remember, that that
is עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. Well, the ר"ן Ran says, go get
לקט שכחה פאה. Leket Shichachah Peah. So clearly the ability to be
provided for from לקט שכחה פאה Leket Shichachah Peah does not make
something not עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, and that's part of what bothers
the גמרא. Gemara So the first answer is, you're right, what makes
it not עינוי נפש inui nefesh is that the husband is not
included. But what the גמרא is saying is that, what the משנה
Mishnah is saying is that in addition to the husband not being
included, you should know that she could also continue to be provided
for from לקט שכחה פאה. Leket Shichachah Peah. Okay, that's answer number
one. Answer number two is, רבא אמר לעולם בעל בכלל
בריות הוא. Rava amar le'olam
ba'al b'chlal briyot hu. Now the husband is included in the נדר,
neder, and she can't be get from the husband. And so there
how do you read the משנה? Mishnah? ומה טעם קאמר, u'mah ta'am
ka'amar, exactly what we didn't want to say is רבא Rava saying
what we are saying. She can't get from anyone, the only source
of her food is לקט שכחה פאה, Leket Shichachah Peah, and that's
enough to make it not עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. מה טעם אין
יכול להפר? Mah ta'am ein yachol lehafer? Why can't he be מפר?
mefer? מפני שיכולה ליהנות בלקט שכחה פאה, mipnei she'yechola lehenot b'Leket Shichachah
Peah, because she can, we'll get to that, because she can be
provided. So this is like a crazy now position. רבי יוסי's Rabbi
Yossi position of עינוי נפש inui nefesh is so super narrow, right,
that even if she says 'I will not get food from anyone
in the world', oh, that's an עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, just go
get it from the I don't know the food bank, go get
it from הפקר. hefker. You know, and therefore it's not עינוי נפש.
inui nefesh. So then the ר"ן Ran says, I don't get it,
what about the storekeeper? Why in the case of the storekeeper is
it עינוי נפש? inui nefesh? Just get it from לקט שכחה פאה.
Leket Shichachah Peah. And he basically says, well maybe we would have
to say, are you ready for this, that the case of the
storekeeper is that it's during the rainy season when there's no לקט
שכחה פאה Leket Shichachah Peah available. But if it's during the the
harvest season and the summer when they there is לקט שכחה פאה,
Leket Shichachah Peah, then she then it doesn't become עינוי נפש inui
nefesh and the husband can't הפר hafer it. Okay, so this is
like a crazy read of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. Something could be
totally denied to her, but if she can get it from הפקר,
hefker, that's not עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. That's what רבא Rava says.
Okay, alright. רב נחמן Rav Nachman goes back to the first position.
רב נחמן אמר לעולם בעל לאו בכלל בריות הוא. Rav Nachman amar
le'olam ba'al lav b'chlal briyot hu. The husband is not amongst בריות.
briyot. When it says 'everybody' it means except you of course. So
therefore he can, it's not עינוי נפש inui nefesh because the husband
can provide. והכי קתני, ve'hachi katani, and here's how to read it.
נתגרשה, nitgarsha, if she gets divorced, then יכולה ליהנות בלקט שכחה פאה.
yechola lehenot b'Leket Shichachah Peah. Then what she's left with is לקט
שכחה פאה Leket Shichachah Peah because that still remains accessible to her.
Now how is what רב נחמן Rav Nachman is saying different than
what עולא Ula said? They both say the husband is not included
in the נדר, neder, she can be provided for by the husband,
and that's why it's not עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. And they both
say that the משנה Mishnah is also saying, by the way, she
can also get from לקט שכחה פאה. Leket Shichachah Peah. So how
are they saying anything different? So the ר"ן says it sounds like
here's the difference. That what's being said is that according to, what
happens if the husband divorces her? When she says 'the husband, when
I meant everybody except you', how long did the 'except you' go
for? Okay, did it mean 'except you because we're married, so obviously
I didn't mean you'? Or does it just mean a categorical 'except
you'? Okay, and that what רב נחמן Rav Nachman is being מחדש
mechadesh is that when she gets divorced, then she does become forbidden
to the husband. Okay, it meant of course when I say everybody
you're part of everybody. The only reason I meant except you was
because right now we're married. But if we were ever not to
be married... you'd go back into the everybody category. Okay? So therefore,
according to רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*, once she gets divorced, she can
no longer even get from the husband, and at that stage, the
only thing available to her is לקט שכחה ופאה *leket shikchah peah*.
That leaves the ר"ן *Ran* into a nice long discussion about what
happens if the circumstances of the נדר neder. *neder* change during the
duration of the נדר neder *neder*. Like you remember גמרא *Gemara* earlier
that if somebody said I won't get any benefit from יורדי הים
*yordei hayam*, from sailors. Let's say somebody became a sailor during the
or stopping a sailor and things changed after the נדר *neder* was
taken. Okay? So he has a question because at least if this
is the way to read רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*, it sounds like
we do reassess. Initially the husband wasn't included in the נדר *neder*,
but then the situation changed and then according to רב נחמן *Rav
Nachman*, he became included in the נדר *neder*, so that would sound
like we would reassess. Although here you could say it's a special
circumstance. You know, it's one thing if I say sailors. Some people
are sailors, some people aren't. Here I said everybody. The husband was
in the, was literally in the everybody category, so it wasn't like
fundamentally he was out and now we're recategorizing him. Fundamentally he was
in the category of the נדר *neder*, but it almost was like
except for the time while we're married. Like except if we're, you
know, so even though fundamentally you're in the נדר *neder*, it's almost
like a little bit of an override since we're still married I
didn't mean it to apply in this situation. So as soon as
that, as that reality of being married goes away, he falls back
into his natural category. So I don't think it's exactly similar to
people who switch categories in the middle. Here, and in some, in
principle, he really was in the category. So we have three opinions:
one is the husband is fundamentally not in the everybody category. Who
was that? The first one, עולא *Ulla*. Then we have רב נחמן
*Rav Nachman* who says the husband isn't in the everybody category as
long as he remains her husband, but once he stops being her
husband, he falls back into the everybody category and he is forbidden,
she is forbidden to get from him. And then רבא *Rava* who
says the husband is in the everybody category and the only reason
this isn't עינוי נפש *inui nefesh* is because she could provide for
from לקט שכחה ופאה *leket shikchah peah*. Yes.
Could you just quickly say that if a
woman prohibits herself, she's,
she can sleep with her husband but not with anybody else and
then if she gets divorced, she can't sleep with anybody else, right,
until it's revoked? Right.
So isn't
there a corollary there to the question of what if somebody's status
changes? So you were just saying a sailor and not a sailor.
Somebody becomes her husband so then does that get overridden just like...
I mean it might be, but there again everybody is still everybody,
right? I mean that was my point. My point was if you
say sailors, some people are sailors, some are not and then what
happens if you switch your identity in the middle? In this case
and in the case you're referring to, she said it's forbidden on
everybody. Well everybody still remains everybody, right? So it's not like you've...
But if somebody's status changes?
Yeah, I mean if somebody becomes her husband, he's still, he was
still in the everybody category, he's still an everybody, right? It's not
as if she said אסור *assur* to my non-husbands and מותר *mutar*
to my husbands, right? That would be different. She did say everybody
in both of those two scenarios. Yes.
So again I guess it's one of the contexts of how we
interpret things because I would have said like, you know, כל הבריות
*kol habriot* or all things are created so she can't even take
a ride on a horse. But you're saying that I guess it's
like, you know, common parlance that it just really means people.
Yes, exactly. So how do you say everything?
It's just like as if they call...
Now I don't know, כל חי *kol chai* maybe, I don't know.
Okay. איתיביה רבא לרב נחמן *Eiteiv Rava le-Rav Nachman* or כל הוה
ואין כל חי *kol hava ve-ein kol chai*. Anyway. איתיביה רבא לרב
נחמן *Eiteiv Rava le-Rav Nachman*, that ultimate human. איתיביה רבא לרב נחמן
*Eiteiv Rava le-Rav Nachman*, so let's just get to the end of
this discussion. So רבא *Rava*, who said בריות *briot* includes everybody, challenged
רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* in the following way. ובעל לאו בכלל בריות
הוא *U-va'al lo be-khlal briot hu*? When you say all creatures, you
don't mean including my husband? והתנן *Ve-ha-tenan*, we learned in the משנה
*Mishnah*: נטויה אני מן היהודים *Netuah ani min ha-yehudim*. See that David,
exactly like you said. A woman says that I am removed from
יהודים *Yehudim*, meaning my, the, you know, I will not get any
sexual pleasure from anybody. יפר חלקו *Yafer chelko*. The husband annuls the
part that refers to him ותשמש עמו *ve-teshamesh immo* and he has
sex with her, or she has sex with him. ותהא אסורה מן
היהודים *Ve-tehei asurah min ha-yehudim* and she remains forbidden to everybody else.
So you see that the husband had to annul the part that
relate... Was that what you were asking David? Maybe I misunderstood. Okay.
Just the switching categories. Okay. Fine. But you see that the husband
was included in that, right? And why don't we just say when
she said I'm forbidden to get sex to have sex from pleasure
from everybody, it means everyone else other than you obviously. Okay? So
nevertheless, no, it's assumed that the husband is included and he has
to annul it. אי אמרת *Ee amart* ובעל לאו בכלל בריות הוא
*u-va'al lo be-khlal briot hu*, if you say the husband is not
included, so therefore, נדרי עינוי נפש הן ויפר לה *nidrei inui nefesh
hen ve-yafer lah*. It's עינוי נפש *inui nefesh* and he should be
מיפר *mefer*. Now... I know, it's a bizarre גרסא *girsa*. There's a
long ר"ן *Ran* that does somersaults to try to explain this גרסא
*girsa*. The ר"ן *Ran* has an alternate גרסא *girsa* which we're just
going to go for for simplicity's sake, which is: ואי אמרת בעל
לאו בכלל בריות הוא אמאי צריך להפר *Ve-ee amart ba'al lo be-khlal
briot hu ammai tzarich le-hafer*? Okay. So we're going to go with
that גרסא *girsa*, which is if the husband... wasn't included, why does
he have to annul his portion? He fundamentally wasn't included. So the
גמרא's answer is: אימא לך, Eima lach, I'll tell you, שאני הכא
דמוכח מילתא. shani hacha demuchach miltha. No, here of course the husband
was included, it's self-evident. דהיתירא קאסרה נפשה. deheteira kaasra nafsha. She, why
does she have to say I can't get sexual pleasure from anybody
else? She already can't get sexual pleasure from anybody else, she's married
to this guy! So in this context, everyone has to include the
husband or else it was completely a meaningless נדר. And therefore, it's
assumed to include the husband and he has to annul. But in
another context, where the נדר is meaningful without including the husband, we
will interpret it to mean everybody other than you, and the husband
would not be included. Okay? And we will end.